<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Economics on DYREHAUGEN</title>
    <link>/categories/economics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Economics on DYREHAUGEN</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/categories/economics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Farewell Globalization</title>
      <link>/post/2021/05/30/farewell-globalization/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021/05/30/farewell-globalization/</guid>
      <description>To solve the Climate Crisis increasing economic productivity and energy efficiency is not sufficient. Absolute decoupling of economic growth and environmental degradition, including global warming is not feasible (Hickel and Kallis (2019) Is Green Growth Possible?). We will have to stop economic growth itself or even degrow on a global scale.
Growth economists have always had models that in the long run end in a steady state. That&amp;rsquo;s just mathematics. Many economists have been thinking about &amp;lsquo;steady state economics&amp;rsquo; for a long time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Case of Norway</title>
      <link>/post/2021/02/26/the-case-of-norway/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021/02/26/the-case-of-norway/</guid>
      <description>Nordic differences My Swedish friend Torbjörn just sent me a paper clip containing a notice of a Swedish economics professor commenting on the economic situation in Norway. Lars Calmfors in DN 22 feb 2021. The notice is triggered by his involvement in a Norwegian Green Paper Commision on Labour and Income Policy. NOU 2019:7. The Commision shouldpropose new measures to increase labour participation in Norway.
Internationally the Nordic (sometimes only Scandinavian) countries are mostly treated as fairly much of the same under the heading of &amp;lsquo;The Nordic Model&amp;rsquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hypergranular Macroeconomics</title>
      <link>/post/2019/01/28/hypergranular-macroeconomics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019/01/28/hypergranular-macroeconomics/</guid>
      <description>The Bruegel blog of September 4, 2018 reports from the annual Jackson Hole gathering of central bankers. This year the focus was on implications for central banks of the rise of superstar firms and changing market structure. Of particular interest I found the contribution of Antoinette Schoar (MIT Sloan) - as refered by Bruegel:
Antoinette Schoar looks at the financial market, argues that the rapid growth of new digital technologies has created a market dynamic, where many institutions outside the central bank system might soon have much more comprehensive, more accurate and also more timely information than the regulators.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Krugmans Explanations</title>
      <link>/post/2018/01/25/krugmans-explanations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018/01/25/krugmans-explanations/</guid>
      <description>Mainstream economics failure to &amp;lsquo;see the crisis coming&amp;rsquo; in 2008 is broadly regarded as a deficiency of the theory. However, Paul Krugman now argues that the theory was - and is - &amp;lsquo;good enough for government&amp;rsquo;. The failure of 2008 was not in the theory, but rather in deficient data collection. Macroeconomists &amp;ldquo;overlooked&amp;rdquo; the institutional changes in the financial sector and did not record appropriate data.
The &amp;ldquo;New Keynesians&amp;rdquo; - i.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
